[Music]
you
but the heart is behind us the windows
hola Teresa hello Daniel
we will make a brief introduction in
Portuguese and as soon as Daniel takes
over he will speak in English with part
of these under titles that it's become a
sahaja dementia português
yeah think you Danielle absolutely
Ellie by following glaze for subtitles
in Portuguese also that learner sort of
Beauty Institute some power could they
know projectors on a Yamaha Turkey
aboard that famous for a general
chemical to delegate to the burner
economy a circle supply ultros you go to
institute MMI system who throughout the
Republic a federal Mellie millennium as
well mr. Aaron Oreo brings aha Danny
Oliver if the main instrument found that
curled you brow he prosperously squadron
hostesses built instituto st. amos same
price processor to digest someplace
famous he listened to the leg of the og
og democracia restaurant to general he's
no pussy Gullu pay my promise to you
Norval mundo you learn was just a mentor
at Rebecca's trapesius create Shiva's
you know fedoras if they're self Emma a
college iya iya suspect Abinadab to some
ecology as a sweet ability versus
deserts most famous for super echo
through compensate to the original
essence of rice your chili for flavor if
I had an excellent Rao when we follow
this dimension to the same original
achieve you in the montage because they
say to progress you know Papa Yamaha
chose to connect so CR as Gigi nos
common samosa Sonia Manifesta a vindaloo
taenia world our breath you you
so next the mythical paint chip initial
that if he could sign her jealousy who
the hell is that sound asleep primero
Fatima could kill Elaine the sustainable
AG and form a to supernova darling whose
evil persona protester solji tada dizzy
my defenses up on war scope atomic shape
nos vemos but faintly this acquaintance
treatise let me say in Kriya yoga de
todos vocês for the study for Moscow
kiritani Agra's sa a Flavia yes hi Eva
Philip most resumed as a perfed here
coming out Daniel Thank You Daniel for
being with us at the cycle we main
character they see Authority diet eating
any doctor largest tomato soup webinar
for civil and commercial is named as
utility orchestra ahem so duccini
professor at reduce awesome Eternia
jelly's in dodgy don't regard that so
does he keep it Jagr this system being
priscilla moneena pelicans own the
others issue a total de todos
with the links Babylon he possible Agra
petha God Apache may be induced by
members welcome everybody is session
taught super maybe English France a care
premier achieve digestive fluid design
engineer achievable was still involve
you Vajrasattva dad schizophrenia window
dude annual Brazil ma su programa son
complete assess Evo pillow no site k www
design regenerative 0.2 or he - on
poking destructor L so ties Amato's vato
facebbok ando es in canoe true
govt she L careful on pokey no
destructor identify Te'o mephala dude
enema placenta soldier say academia
order the poise identified to us for
best to prepare
Esther's in town cage that a winter
proof of or Calaca presentation as a
Kachina GE Q&A payment as a hodgepodge
dish I know we have people from all over
watching us at this moment so you are
all very welcome
we'll have a 30 minutes presentation
with Daniel and then we'll be we'll have
an open space for questions and answers
if you have a question you can just type
it in our Q&A box but I can proceed
serjilla gender as interesting as water
gushing a key match look how close it
caption a search of a cashier give us a
bite there a legenda impulse to gauge
with any wife as a present a sound daily
English so then I will be speaking
English and the ones who need
translations you have to activate your
closed caption box okay you sue in town
well mom huh I present a proposed say so
Daniel Daniel a consult or a baccardo
Yom Tov do live through designing
regenerative cultures Kim Bradley Sarah
publicado Brazil related horrible Wow
some sort super contains cancer
well Sahel is Assam Cara Grande co-chief
is they are missing pointer to Sevilla
special matey
I'll get Institute an expert out then I
will be all of them a mastering Saints
as Alicia Kashia doto InDesign not
without a human grand experience such
massive engines stood on enough videos I
used to stay Amish ecologic wish if I
actually OSHPD answer wasn't it's an
honor to present you Daniel Daniel
you're very welcome
thank you so much for being here with us
thank you very much for everybody who
made this possible and thank you so much
for everybody who's decided to spend the
next hour with us here on line I'm quite
amazed that we will have simultaneous
subtitling and I will
speak a lot slower than I normally speak
because there is a certain delay of
course with the translation and then the
typing and so if you find me speaking a
little bit slow it's not because I think
slow it's because it makes it easier for
the translator so initially I'll use a
little presentation and then I'll switch
back to the screen so let me just see
how I can share my screen with you
a month
compartir okay so the theme of today's
webinar which is the first of two
webinars before my visit to Brazil is
why go beyond sustainability and as
Taizo has already mentioned I wrote a
book which was published in 2016 called
each designing regenerative cultures and
in the last two-and-a-half years the
uptake of this idea of moving beyond
sustainability and exploring what it
might be to act regenerative Li has
really taken the world by storm more and
more people are interested in this and
this is really what we're gonna explain
or explore today together since we're
hosted by the Goethe Institute and my
native language is actually German spent
most of my life away from Germany but I
was born in Germany and I I am German I
would like to start with this quote by
Johann Wolfgang von Goethe who lived
between 1749 and 1832
but in 1869 when the journal Nature the
scientific journal nature was first
published T H Huxley the geographer no
geologist was asked to write the
introduction to this first edition of
nature and he chose to quote Goethe at
length and I'm just reading a small
section from this quote
nature who cannot see her everywhere
sees her nowhere in the right light the
spectacle of nature is always new for
she is always renewing the spectators
life is her most exquisite invention and
death is her expert contrivance to get
plenty of life she is complete but never
unfinished and to me this quote very
much speaks to nature and life being a
regenerative community it is a process
that continuously renews the possibility
for more life to occur on the planet and
if we look at the history of evolution
we can see that life has actually
improved the conditions for more life to
be possible and what kind of a
civilization would we create as human
beings if we did the same if we asked
ourselves can we as life create
conditions conducive to life can we
leave a richer more abundant more
diverse more productive planet to future
generations then we received from our
fathers and grandfathers and
grandmothers and and mothers
and that's really in a nutshell for me
what working regenerative Li is all
about um I don't want to spend a lot of
time on the bad news I just feel it's
necessary to stress that we're at a very
critical point in human history we are
currently when we have been for a very
long time in ecological overshoot
sometime in the 1970s we started using
more resources every year then we can
that the earth can regenerate in one
year so by now
in early August every year humanity has
used up the resources and the capacity
to absorb waste that the planet has and
is going yet again into overshoot is
stealing resources from future
generation is eroding and degrading the
inheritance of 3.8 million a billion
years of life evolution on earth
obviously that can go can't go on
forever and we have to rollback
overshoot day every year a little bit
until we live within the bioproductive
capacity of Earth every year we'll also
at a point where runaway climate changes
now a real possibility possibly already
upon us and the window of opportunity to
respond to climate change and possibly
reverse it so within the next three or
four decades we can actually
restabilized climate and create a
regenerative future for many more
centuries and millennia to come the
window of opportunity is closing we're
already in planetary overshoot where
we're and there's a number of planetary
boundaries that we're transgressing and
we still in most societies have not
managed to build the social foundations
the graphic on the top right is the
famous donut from donut economics from
kate ray worth did
speaks to this issue that we're
basically neither have the social
foundations right nor are we within
ecological boundaries and the graphic at
the bottom right that you can see is
expressing the injustice on the planet
and the inequality on the planet it's
not only that just recently another
paper was published at 26 billionaires
on the planet now own as much money as
half of the world's population together
it's also that the top 10% most wealthy
people on the planet are responsible for
50% of the carbon emissions and the
bottom 50% of global poor together only
emits about 10% of the carbon emissions
so as we're facing climate change and
those who had the least
to do with it are going to suffer the
greatest and that is a kind of
inequality and unfairness it will not
continue into the future and that we do
have to address
so let me use this framework that isn't
my framework but it's um it's it's a
wonderful way of understanding what
we're talking about when we talk about
regeneration this comes from Carol
Sanford bill Reid Pamela Mann and Ben
Haggard the Regenesis group I have
Reid's permission to use this graph it's
in my book and today it's not fully
translated I have to apologize that some
of my slides a mix of languages and I
actually used Google Translate so for
those who speak Portuguese there might
be the odd mistake but basically what
this graph is trying to express is that
as we move from business as usual the
current degenerative system that we're
all part of towards sustainability and a
regenerative system we were moving up
this spiral from the bottom left to the
top right and the conventional practice
that we're engaged in at the moment is
basically keeping within regulations not
breaking the law but it's not it's not
it's still adding an almost months of
damage then the next step is to be a
little bit green to voluntarily choose
to have less of an impact than is
legally allowed and many companies
you
understands this as a step on a path and
so in the same way sustainable is a step
on the path to regeneration so when we
speak about regenerative design and
regenerative development we're not
saying that we don't need sustainability
it's still a goal ahead of us but if you
define sustainability as not adding any
more damage to the system then we've now
come to a point where that's simply not
enough anymore because we've done so
much damage over centuries and even
millennia then we need to undo the
damage of the past and we need to heal
ecosystems and heal the planet in order
to have a healthier human presence on
earth and I know and I want to stress
this that there are lots of people who
have worked very hard their entire lives
within sustainable development and
sustainability that actually have a
regenerative attitude towards how they
work on sustainability so let's not
start creating another dualism of saying
sustainability is not good anymore and
it's all has to be regenerative we need
to celebrate both but in this spectrum
if you move on you then get to a
restorative attitude where you where you
try to undo the damage but if it is done
still with the mindset of the engineer
who does something to nature it can lead
to problems very quickly where we do
large-scale replantation of certain
trees that might not fit that particular
place and might not be adapted to the
local water availability and then you
plant a million trees and only very few
of them survive so unless we become more
humble and really understand that this
separation that we have been taught
culturally that somehow culture and
nature are separate is a false dualism
it's a false separation we have never
been separate from nature we are as
biological beings part of nature and so
there's this step of reconciliation of
putting humanity back into the community
of life and when we start working from
that understanding that we are capable
as life to create conditions conducive
to life then we're beginning to move
into designing as nature and then we're
beginning to look at working
regenerative Li and
you can see on that graph is basically
everything once we move above the x-axis
we're taking a living systems approach
that guides design and innovation we
collaborate for
shared abundance and we create
conditions conducive to life what we're
doing right now is we're creating
degenerative conditions with our
economic systems our transport systems
the way we house ourselves and our
industries and we're also in a system
that is competing for artificially
created scarcity and we fragment
knowledge and our awareness of this
whole of in which we participate in a
way that it leads to insufficiently good
design and innovation so that's roughly
the framework
and to give you an example that is very
much related to climate changes that how
do we heal the planet how do we heal
degraded ecosystems this graphic shows
that as soon as you like the current way
of land management and industrial
agriculture have degraded our soils have
impoverished our soils have impoverished
biodiversity and so there's a whole set
of less less ground cover means less
roots in the ground less biomass in the
ground means less carbon in the ground
means less capacity for the soil to
capture water and and let it infiltrate
the aquifer it increases erosion it
decreases bio productivity in
biodiversity and it means that more
carbon is released to the atmosphere
and so we're driving climate change so
that's on the right on the Left if we
use holistic Land Management and we use
techniques from regenerative agriculture
we can do exactly the reverse if you
double the amount of carbon in the soil
you 20-fold increase the capacity of the
soil to retain water so when it rains
the soil is like a sponge and it takes
up all the water and then it can trickle
into the aquifer again and replenish it
the images that you can see on the right
of this slide images from the Loess
Plateau in China which is a vast area of
3500 square kilometres and in 1994 the
Chinese government started to
toward this area which is a very dry
calcareous
eroded landscape almost a desert and
between 1994 and 2009 they managed to
regenerate 175 square kilometres of the
loose plateau in the way that you see in
these images for me this is a very
hopeful image because it shows that we
are actually capable of healing
ecosystems and of increasing
biodiversity bio productivity and the
health of ecosystems functions
and there are a number of exam
this also happening in Brazil the one
that I came across
today is the Sebastian Salgado who's a
famous photographer and his wife decided
in the late 90s to buy a thinker from
from their family and to start
replanting the much Atlantic at the
Atlantic rainforest and he can see here
the 2001 to 2019 image is impressive and
they've transformed the landscape
they've planted over 2.7 million trees
on that piece of land they've restored
one hundred one thousand seven hundred
and forty acres what happened after
years of doing that is that the springs
came back because the water could filter
into the ground and so an area that was
drying up suddenly had Springs running
again at 20 20 litres per minute and
they have massively increased the
biodiversity of that area there are
other projects all over the world that
tried to do the same thing there's an
organization in the Netherlands called
common land that has pilot projects in
Australia and South Africa and the
Netherlands in Spain and soon in Mexico
and they're basically building
multi-stakeholder partnerships between
land owners of degraded land at the
regional scale working by originally and
then they create they agree on a 25-year
process of regenerating and restoring
that land because nature works in
different time scales than our human
economic cycles and to really heal an
ecosystem much can be done in the first
8 to 10 years but to really do it in the
long term it means it takes about 25
years and within this initiative of
common land sits another wonderful
initiative which is called the
ecosystems restoration camps and the
first one was started here in I live in
Spain it was started in Spain and in new
Murcia and soon there will be another
one in Mexico
and it's basically an opportunity for
people from all over the world to come
to a place and learn how to regenerate
and restore ecosystems to learn
practical permaculture to learn how to
em
bring like the soil back to life and how
to replant and how to increase the
biodiversity but to do so in ways that
actually become bio productive and
they're also increase the the regional
economy health and the the local social
fabric because a lot of these places get
abandoned people move away from the
countryside because it becomes so
non-productive and once you regenerate
the land you get a return and social
capital you get a return in natural
capital you get a return in inspiration
and you get a economic return after the
initial startup phase and
we also it's not just about
restoring the land it's also about
changing the way that we inhabit the
planet by now there's more than 50% of
human beings living in cities and
there's a lot of work already being done
on what a regenerative city would look
like and basically I'm just taking you
very briefly through the history of
cities we used to live in cities that
were a group Alice there were cities
very closely connected to agriculture in
their local region so the city was
intimately linked to its regions and
most of the things that were produced
and consumed in that city came from
local resources there was always some
trade but it was a small proportion of
what people needed to meet their daily
needs what we've done with the onset of
using fossil fuels and fossil resources
is we've changed a group a list to
petrópolis there's an image of sao paulo
on the top there a classic petrópolis
mega city where there's very little
connection to the local bio region and
most resources come in from all over the
planet and the the city and the region
have lost contact to a large degree and
the challenge now is to move into a
future of an eco palace where we still
have where the city is not powered by
petrol anymore the city's is powered by
renewable energy renewable energy that
is generated decentralized in the city
and around the city but also the main
basic needs of the city for water
sovereignty for food solvent sovereignty
food for basic materials that are needed
to meet the needs of the population is
returning to the region and a symbiotic
relationship between the city and the
region is actually helping to restore
the land around the city but also bring
nature back into the city um the
Austrian architect wounded Vasa
supposedly said once that in a city any
surface where snow could kill
in a in a snowfall any surface that is
horizontal should be green so when you
look at the city from above it should be
not very different from looking at
metals or forests from above and the
architect Stefano burly from very from
Italy is currently designing a forest
city in China that you can see on that
little image on the top right there
which is basically hiding the city under
a forest it's important to recognize
that we need to do more retrofitting
rather than build these futuristic new
cities because really we need to deal
with the cities we've already got but
how do we do this
it's basically applying the concept of
the circular economy to the city and the
bio region and to rather than have the
city draw in resources from all over the
planet like the ecological footprint of
the City of London is about a hundred
and twenty-five times as big as the
actual physical footprint of the city
and that's obviously not sustainable
cities cover only 3% three to four
percent of the Earth's land surface but
they use eighty percent of the resources
and produce eighty percent of the
greenhouse gas emissions so cities is
where a lot of these issues will be
tested
and the future that we're moving into as
we're and this is really the challenge
of regenerative design to redesign the
human presence on earth within the next
generation like within our generation
from a degenerative impact an
exploitative impact to designing a human
relationship to the ecosystems we
inhabit that is healing and regenerative
and if you look at the map now of the
world there's lots of straight lines
that were drawn by colonialists that
said okay this is where this country
ends and the next country starts these
lines have nothing to do with the bio
cultural uniqueness of place they were
introduced in the era of empires of
power over of dividing people and
dividing humanity into other nations so
we can more easily be controlled by
rulers as we move into the planetary era
the future where we simply have to
recognize that we are
passengers on human spaceship earth and
that we better learn how to deal well
with this living spaceship earth we need
to redesign our patterns of how we meet
our ecosystems in ways that actually
connect to the ecosystem and this
wonderful map that you see in front of
you is a map by Robert Zuke's that shows
all the aquifers and watersheds of the
world's rivers systems even in the
deserts their aquifers underneath the
desert and if we redesign our
presence on earth in
with these watersheds then the the
patterns become natural patterns again I
personally believe that the nation-state
is an anachronism that doesn't serve us
in
moving into a truly regenerative
civilization on earth but it will take a
long time to erode these patterns of
nation-states but I think that in the
22nd century we will be diversely
adapted regenerative cultures that are
adapted to the bio cultural uniqueness
of the bio regions they inhabit and
nation-states will be less important so
this is a shift in worldview a shift in
the missile Roman law and
circular relationship between what we
design and how we see the world how we
see the world influences what we think
we need and how we design what we design
and who we design for and then the
designs go on designing they shape our
world and they also shape our experience
in our consciousness and and so if we
shift worldview through education we
shift how we design and we can bring
about this redesign of the human
presence on earth and and I've also put
in for those of you who are familiar
with guy education and that's why guy
education has a four dimensional
approach to designing for sustainability
and regenerative design for the last 15
years
we've always emphasized the importance
of worldview in all this and the last
thing I want to share with you before we
open for questions is something that
happened when I was on the masters and
holistic science at Shu Maha College
which was in 2001 and 2002 and
relatively early on in the course in
September 2001 the horrific attacks
attacks on the World Trade Centers in
New York happened and of course that was
a disruption that we're still we're
still in a different world since that
happened today and um so the day after
September 12 2001 we had a session with
the nine students on the masters and
with Stefan Harding and Brian Goodwin
and our tutor Jody PGM and Jody wrote
read two poems by Ted not on one of them
was the wonderful piece on interbeing
and the other one is called call me by
my true names which I highly recommend
you look up and and and read and then we
discussed
the the bifurcation point that the
critical point in history that we were
at after this attack and how you could
react to such a attack and that you
could either react from fear or from
love and so we developed in a wonderful
dynamic way this map which I think
describes very well what the shift
towards regenerative cultures is all
about so we've lived in a culture where
science has homogenized has put
disciplines into silos has looked at
fractions parts of the system has tried
to like our economic system tries to
maximize particular parts economic gain
with in inefficient measures of success
like the gross domestic product and
we've created a culture that only looks
at the benefits for individuals and of
course this then goes on to create
alienation it is a expression of the
separation from the world and it creates
a separation between culture and nature
and from this we get an even stronger
need for like we begin to compete we
want to predict and control because we
with fear nature as other or other
people and and we feel separated and
that then drives that vicious cycle
but if we
to search for a deeper meaning because
that is actually not fulfilling us to
just run after the money and we become
playful and creative together we realize
we can create collaborative abundance
and we shift into the virtuous cycle of
love of being valuing diversity of
understanding that even if we don't
agree the diversity of all of us seeing
the world from slightly different angles
gives us more information about this
wonderful complex dynamic system in
which we participate and so we begin to
optimize the whole four benefits for the
collective and the individual and we do
so through collaboration participation
and co-creation and it gives us in a
sense of belonging in a sense of place
we connect with the story of place again
and we begin to share deeper meaning
what it is like to be life and as life
create conditions conducive to life and
I think that for me that sums up quite
well what culture shift we need to bring
about as quickly as possible and I'm
really excited to be able to come to
Brazil in March and share these ideas
with more people and there's so many
people already working regenerative lis
around Brazil and in Central and South
America and I really feel that we are
the regeneration the generation that
regenerates rising and I mean we from
young people like Greta turn back was
recently taken the world by storm by
speaking truth to power in at the
climate summit and now in the World
Economic Forum but it's the young people
the Millennials our generation my
generation I'm in my 40s but also the
wise elders that I've learned from weed
we're all having to come together to
create this fundamental shift of the
human presence on earth and I would love
it if you all joined in the regeneration
rising because I have a little
that is 18 months old and I wanted her
to grow up in a world that is more
abundant and more rich and healthier
than the world that I inherited from my
grandparents so let's do it
thank you so much and I'm looking
forward to your questions
just one more thing maybe we can come
share this presentation with everybody
who's interested if you want to get in
touch with me or if you want to follow
me on any of this social media um please
do so on thank you
Thank You Daniel thank you so much we
have many questions much demos various
speakers and I think to start I can
share this one with you
sustainability evolves many many
different areas because beyond the
environment how can we address the
regenerative design to to these other
areas for example community development
or economic systems if you could talk a
little bit about this one of the of
course you're absolutely right it's just
as sustainability has four dimensions so
does regenerative practice and actually
very often doing the ecological
regeneration can give a shared meaning
that then leads to social more social
cohesion and social regeneration and it
creates local opportunities business
opportunities and innovation
opportunities it reconnects read region
Eliza's INRI localizes economic systems
in such a way that it also is
economically regenerative the scale at
which regeneration best happens is at
the scale of communities and bio regions
and the fundamental shift both in terms
of the social regeneration and in terms
of the economics regeneration is to stop
thinking in terms of competitive
advantage and to start thinking in terms
of collaborative advantage
we've been culturally trained to think
we need to compete we
even tell a miss misunderstood story of
how nature works and say that nature is
full of competition but the reality is
that 90% of the interactions in the
natural world are collaborative and
symbiotic and competition is just the
way to find you in the system it's the
ripples on the ocean that waves but the
depth of the entire ocean of life is
collaboration
great Thank You Daniel we have many
others I'll tell you a few of them one
is related to the Agra forest systems if
they are considered as regenerative
design experience and what would be
other experiences and it's also related
to the question how could we reintroduce
the regenerative design in in
conservation environmental conservation
unities I'm not sure if it's familiar
so agroforestry and analog forestry are
key elements of regenerative ecological
practices um I I have the wonderful good
fortune to be on the jury of the lush
spring prize which is a prize for
ecological and social regeneration that
happens so far it has happened every
year it will soon start happening every
second year and in a couple of weeks
time I'm going to London - together with
the other 12 judges to decide who's
going to be the winner in 2019 and many
of the projects that make it into the
finalists are agroforestry projects
there's usually a number of applicants
from Brazil last year there were two
winners from Brazil and agroforestry is
a key practice and in terms of it is a
regenerative practice already but if we
look at this approach that I briefly
mentioned the common land foundations
approach is - in terms of regeneration
environmental restoration practice it is
about creating biosphere reserves that
really leave nature to herself a
mortared them the more than human nature
to herself so that so nature can
generate its own abundance and then have
buffer zones around it of mixed use with
agroforestry system that where we begin
to be more productive but of course many
of you are probably already familiar
with the fact that that now research
shows that even the
the densest parts of the Amazon
rainforest I actually a forest garden
system that were in part cultivated by
the human beings that lived as nature
and designed as nature within them I
think it's really important to remember
that when we talk about regenerative
practice we're actually also bringing
back indigenous practices in indigenous
wisdom that has meant that as human
beings we used to live by originally and
we used to live and design as nature and
we've just lost our path a little bit
and we need to come back to this kind of
practice and and basically creating
corridors between these buffer zones
connecting the the system again in such
a way that animal migration can continue
to happen and in systems become vibrant
again and there's exchange so depleted
areas actually have influx of new
biodiversity from other areas it's all
part of the system it's not it's like
all these practices are part of what we
now talk about as regenerative practice
but they they might be much older than
the name regeneration I hope that makes
it clear
Thank You Daniel there are many many
questions I'm not sure if we'll be able
to address all of them one question is
about is someone is asking you to bring
to give more examples about projects
related to the regenerative culture and
someone else asked it if you have any
example in this concept being used in
human relations mmm-hmm
so in terms of big examples of course in
a 30 minute webinar and and 25 minute
question-and-answer I can't really cover
all the examples that I know of but my
book designing regenerative cultures
which I am sure that the beginning has
is full of examples and the easiest way
to find more examples is to go onto my
medium block which if you just put
Daniel Christian ball and medium it'll
come up in your search engine and there
are 320 articles on there that all give
examples in social examples economic
examples ecological examples and some of
them are excerpts from Gaia education
curriculum in for the online course some
of them are excerpts from my book from
my master's thesis from my PhD and
things that I've written in the last
couple of years and so I I think I would
end up speaking too long if I went into
lots of specific examples right now but
please do look them up and also I would
give more examples in the next webinar
and I will also give a lot more examples
when when I'm in in Brazil and of course
if if you think of just the last part of
your question Thai supposed and human
relationships if you just look at that
last slide that shift from the vicious
the virtuous a vicious cycle of fear to
the virtuous cycle of love and that
clearly is applicable to human
relationships it's it's asking yourself
in in interpersonal relationships but
also in business relationships but with
other enterprises when you feel that
impulse that we've
so been trained in to see oh this person
is trying to get onto my turf my area em
and you feel competitive to just kind of
go oh wow that's wonderful there's
another person who actually does the
same thing than I than I do maybe we
could do something together that would
be more where the hole would be more
than the sum of its parts where together
we could achieve something that neither
one of us could achieve alone and so you
shift from that attitude of competition
to the attitude of collaboration and you
really try to work on em what responding
to the person would be like from a
collaborative space and I think that
that's a it's a spiritual and a social
practice um that will bring about a
better world
in cue Daniel there are so many
questions that I just don't know what to
do with all of them but I will read some
of them
if regenerative design can be applied in
product development industry if you know
examples about experience specific
working with children how can we
communicate this message the
regeneration message - governs and
corporations how can we spread this kind
of practices ok many other specific ones
ok the next the next webinar will be on
nature inspired design and so I'll speak
a lot more about the different scales of
design from from material science to
product design to Architecture Community
Design regional like open design and by
regional planning and but of course one
of the key elements there is to look at
the entire supply chain to shorten the
supply chain to shift from fossil
materials to bio materials that are
regenerative Lee grown to shift from
producing with fossil energy to
producing with renewable energy and to
always ask yourself as a company and as
a product designer how does this product
sit in the scale linking interconnected
dynamics system that is life as a
planetary process and can we redesign
our products and our businesses in such
a way that they actually regenerate
rather than degrade the system and in
terms of working with children right
it's not like nothing comes to mind but
of course there's education is key from
the absolute beginning and I'm thinking
of Kunta Polly's wonderful collection of
fables for young children that teach
children basic ethics teach children
were Fritjof Capra called the system's
view of life and
bring at a very early age an
understanding of this inter being in
this interconnectedness of the system of
how nature creates abundance through
symbiosis and collaboration and there
are wonderful examples of schools that
do that
I'm actually not now that I'm talking
about it there's a place in Norway
called the small earth Institute which
is run by a friend of mine who basically
wants to bring regenerative head
educational practices into schools so
you might want to look that up okay
thank you we have less than 10 minutes
so I think we you might be able to
answer maybe one more question one thing
that we that we could potentially do is
I think you can save the all the
questions that were in the chat and you
can send it to me as a text file and I
can't promise it but I can try to create
a medium post answering some of those
questions and in writing so if if you
are out there listening and yeah your
question hasn't been answered maybe in a
couple of it'll take probably about
three weeks because I'm very busy the
next two weeks but I'll try to get back
to it and I'll publish something on
medium answering some more questions
that sounds great that's perfect
we have many questions related also to
to economic systems how we would apply
these concepts to to create new economic
systems and yeah many people are asking
for more examples and so on I think you
already said about the the next
activities but maybe we can also with
regard to regenerative economics I
should definitely mention the wonderful
work of the capital Institute in New
York John Fullerton and Stuart Cohen and
and now Joe Brewer working with them as
well and basically what the capital
Institute has done is they launched in
2000 and was at 16 or 15 the white paper
on towards the regenerative economic
system and then eventually it was
actually called regenerative capitalism
I know a lot of people are allergic to
the world's capital and capitalism and
just as much as a lot of people are
allergic to the word growth but I think
M F as we of course the current economic
growth is part of the degenerative
process that is driving fundamentally
our degenerative practices but we can
shift from the quantitative economic
growth to a qualitative
biological growth of healthy ecosystems
and still create regenerative economies
that grow in quality of human
relationships grow in quality of the
biomaterials produced grow and grow in
the quantity and quality of the bio
productivity and what is transpiring as
the capital Institute now has launched a
network of regional hubs of people
committing in a specific buyer region
different countries around the world to
drive this idea of regionally centered
generative economies and where nobody
really knows exactly how to do this but
we are beginning to ask the questions
were beginning to look at the patterns
that would increase collaboration in the
system would increase resilience at the
regional level would increase food and
energy sovereignty and all these pieces
fit together and then diversify the
local economy one one example that is
wonderful is in in the city of
Philadelphia Judy wakes and bally the
Business Alliance for local living
economies and then also the wonderful
work of Helena Novick Hodge and local
futures she's been a pioneer of the
regenerative of the re localization and
re regionalization movements so uhm
please have a look at that and again my
blog is full of examples for those
people who want more specific examples
Dicer that sounds great Thank You Daniel
thank you so much I think we must stop
for now yes it's almost 5:00 here in
Brazil and I would like to thank you so
much for being with us
II and to thank all of you Cairo grad si
muy to la vez esto a douche agente Akuma
said it pay us 1000 G new mini move inch
between Taysom eyes which my sister
matches undisputed Amanda and Oprah
Daniel Kelly Pradesh on daily Vipond am
presently sagir George pmos uno soprano
webinar fashion Dada's approaches inches
Cinco de fevereiro no measure REO sobre
design B us tie rod o algo más preguntas
upon say he spawns EDA's no pros man
webinar yajante emissary judge Vedad
previous durante vendo do do pro brazil
elevate equation C do G of enjoys el
treinta un de ma su mo sativa dodges
free vistas in San Paulo you know huge
an arrow pulling quanto he on course
makes Evo polyesters workshops a concept
there's a change of equation EG y
accompany todo SE when cement to daniel
trans-border
super frizzy hair already searched every
herb this price event o in Maputo
Mozambique he can be hubs no he January
in San Paulo para noise
mmm ha ha Elizondo is CSS a DJ man
scatting Shama cichlids I'm a generous
Evo eaten being would be Razi todo todo
squeeze melt sobre cut orogeny receive a
design he generate non so pro Brazil
Mirage 5 zg lingua
Cara Grande Samui tattoed skiff company
then you'll thank you so much it was
great to have you with us again can I
just say one more thing because it's so
central and so important and it answers
some of the questions and when I started
to write my book and I very quickly got
to that point of saying what is it what
examples can I put here what what
solutions what answers can I put here
that will be meaningful in 10 12 15 20
years time and I very quickly realized
that maybe we've got it wrong as a
culture being so obsessed with solutions
and answers they're important but really
a wise culture that moves regenerative
ly into the future should pay more
attention to the questions than the
answers and my book has 250 questions in
it and maybe the most important
take-home lessons of creating
regenerative cultures is that we need to
learn to live these questions together
they're all questions that we have to
make
meaningful to us to our community to the
specifics of our place so we connect
again to each other and to the unique
wonderful places we inhabit and so the
essence of if I say life is a
regenerative community if for human
beings the essence of regenerative
practice for me is the personal
development the community capacity
development and I think it's about
living the questions together so that's
what I wanted to leave you with and
thank you again
Taizo for facilitating and for everybody
who made this possible thank you so much
thank you yagura de soto de chimie tava
key trauma lianca jangchigi trundle son
Elysian dodging so they keep it apart a
portrait of nice so possible my Cobra
Gaza
yeah tell preserve its into the video
thank you all
[Music]
you